Smell that?
Vous sentez ça ?
That's the smell of new comic books.
C'est l'odeur de nouveaux comics.
Oh. yes.
Oh, oui.
They're on me today. boys.
C'est moi qui régale, aujourd'hui.
You're paying? Have you been selling your sperm again?
Tu paies ? Tu as encore vendu ton sperme ?
No. I'm celebrating.
Je fête un événement.
As we speak. the space shuttle is docking at the International Space Station...
La navette spatiale s'arrime a la station internationale
...where it will deploy the Wolowitz Zero-Gravity Waste Disposal System.
où sera déployé le système d'élimination des déchets Wolowitz.
Oh. get over yourself. It's a high-tech toilet.
T'emballe pas pour des toilettes high tech.
Just think. thanks to your hard work...
Grâce à ton travail,
...an international crew of astronauts will boldly go where no man has gone before.
des astronautes vont, au mépris du danger, se lâcher dans l'inconnu.
-|s that supposed to be funny? -I believe it is.
- C‘est censé être drôle ? - Je trouve.
The Star Trek reference and the play on words...
La référence a Star Trek et le jeu de mots :
...involving the double meaning of “to go“...
"se lâcher“ dans ”l‘inconnu”,
...suggest that Leonard is humorously mocking your efforts in space plumbing.
suggèrent que Léonard se moque de ton talent de plombier spatial.
Okay. make your little jokes. But of the four of us...
Vous pouvez rire. Mais de nous quatre,
...l'm the only one making any real-world contribution to science and technology.
je suis le seul a travailler dans la science et la technologie.
He's right. This is an important achievement for two reasons:
C‘est une réussite pour deux raisons :
Number one. and of course. number two.
petite et grosse commission.
Oh. clever.
Trés malin.
Playing on the use of cardinal numbers as euphemisms for bodily functions.
Un calembour fondé sur un homonyme confondant le travail
Here. Sheldon. I pulled the new Hellbuy for you.
Je t'ai gardé le dernier Hellboy.
lt's mind-blowing.
Il est épatant.
Excuse me. spoiler alert.
Pas de révélations précoces.
But I didn't spoil anything.
Je n'ai rien révélé.
You told me it's mind-blowing. so my mind is going into it pre-blown.
Il est épatant. je me prépare donc a être épaté.
And once a mind is pre-blown. it cannot be re-blown.
Une fois préparé, la surprise est gâchée.
-|'m sorry. -Said the Grinch to Christmas.
- Désolé. - Dit Ie Grinch à Noël.
-Hey. can I talk to you about something? -Sure. What's up?
- Je peux te dire un mot ? - Qu'y a-t-il ?
Remember I went out with Penny a couple weeks ago?
Tu te souviens que je suis sorti avec Penny ?
Yeah. vaguely.
Oui, vaguement.
Sure. you remember. That was the night...
Mais si. Ce soir—là, tu es sorti.
What about it?
Qu'y a-t-il ?
Well. the thing is. the date didn't go that well.
Ce rancard ne s‘est pas trés bien passé.
I guess the thing to do now is. you know. pick yourself up.
Il ne te reste plus qu'à t'en remettre.
Dust yourself off. forget it. Move on.
Oublier et passer a autre chose.
-I can't do that. -Why the hell not?
- Impossible. - Allons bon !
Because we're going out again tomorrow.
On ressort ensemble demain.
Excuse me. Stuart?
Excuse-moi, Stuart ?
-Have you read the new Flash? -No.
- As-tu lu le dernier Flash ? - Non.
Well. l have. and it will knock your socks off.
Moi, si, et il va te décoiffer.
Good luck getting them back on.
Amuse—toi a te recoiffer.
Anyway. I figure this is probably my last shot with Penny...
C‘est ma dernière chance avec Penny.
-...and I don't wanna screw it up. -Oh. nobody wants that.
- et je ne veux pas la gâcher. - Quelle idée !
So here's my question:
Voilà ma question :
It's the second date. You think she'll be expecting things to get physical?
Au 2e rancard, voudra-t-elle que ce soit physique ?
Oh. gee.
Mince.
Yeah. my initial reaction is no.
lnstinctivement, je dirais non.
Okay. So you'll give me a call?
Bien, tu m'appelles ?
-Yeah. or you call me. -Great.
- Oui, ou toi. - Super.
Or nobody calls anyone.
Ou personne.
Interesting. Penny's current suitor asking advice from her former suitor.
Intéressant, Ie soupirant de Penny demande conseil a son ex soupirant.
Yeah. thanks for closed-captioning my pain. Raj.
Merci d‘avoir sous—titré ma douleur, Ra].
You wanna make sure he gets nowhere with Penny...
Tu veux qu'il se plante avec Penny,
...without jeopardizing your friendship with either of them?
sans menacer ton amitié avec eux ?
-|'m listening. -Just tell him...
- Je t'écoute. - Dis—lui
...to do everything you've done with her for the last two years.
de faire ce que tu as fait avec elle depuis deux ans.
-Hey. Leonard. -Oh. hi.
- Salut, Leonard. - Salut.
-How's it going? -Good. good.
- Ça va ? - Bien.
-You? -Fine.
- Et toi ? - Ça va.
-Oh. yeah. hey. can I ask you something? -Sure.
- J'ai une question a te poser. - Oui.
You know your friend Stuart?
Ton ami Stuart.
Yes.
Oui.
Well. he asked me out again and I said yes.
Il m‘a invitée et j'ai accepté.
And then I started thinking maybe I should talk to you first.
Je pense que j'aurais dû te demander.
-About what? -Well. does it bother you?
- Comment ca ? - Ça t'embête ?
Me going out with one of your friends?
Que je sorte avec ton ami ? Comme on était...
I'm really more of a right now kind of guy.
Je vis dans le présent.
You know. living in the moment.
L‘instant présent.
Although I do have to live a little in the future because. well. that's my job.
Mais aussi un peu dans le futur, car c‘est mon boulot.
Of course. my fondness for classic science fiction...
Ma passion pour la sci-fi classique m'oriente vers le passé,
...but those stories often take place in the future. so--
mais ca se passe dans le futur, donc...
In conclusion. no. it doesn't bother me.
Bref, ça ne m'embête pas.
Okay. well. that's really cool of you.
C‘est sympa de ta part.
LEONARD: Yeah? Well. I wouldn't say cool.
Je ne dirais pas ca.
I'd just say. “That's Leonard.“
Je dirais plutôt : "C‘est Léonard tout craché.“
Well. in that case. do you mind giving me some advice?
Tu aurais un conseil a me donner ?
About Stuart?
Pour Stuart ?
Love to.
Avec plaisir.
He's very shy. How do | make him feel more comfortable around me?
Il est trés timide. Comment le mettre a l'aise ?
Well. first of all. don't underestimate the value of discomfort.
D'abord, ne sous-estime pas la valeur du malaise.
-ReaHy? -Well. yeah.
- Vraiment ? - Il s'épanouit sous pression.
That's why he works in a comic-book store.
Il est vendeur de comics.
lt's Stuart.
C‘est Stuart.
You're not going to answer it?
Tu ne réponds pas ?
He wants to talk about Penny. I don't wanna talk about Penny.
Il veut parler de Penny. Je ne veux pas.
You're making an assumption.
C‘est une supposition.
Perhaps the comic book store is on fire.
Le magasin peut être en feu.
And he needs your assistance.
Il peut avoir besoin d‘aide.
Why would he call me?
Pourquoi m‘appeler ?
We don't know.
On ne sait pas.
And if you don't answer the phone. we can't know.
Si tu ne réponds pas, on ne saura jamais.
I'm not answering the phone. Sheldon.
Je ne répondrai pas au téléphone.
-Answer the phone. Leonard. -No.
- Réponds, Leonard. - Non.
There. It went to voicemail.
Voilà. Le répondeur.
Aren't you going to check your messages?
Tu ne vérifies pas tes messages ?
-No. -You have to check your messages.
- Non. - Tu dois les Vérifier.
The leaving of a message is one half of a social contract...
Laisser un message est un contrat social
...which is completed by the checking of the message.
qui est respecté quand on l‘écoute.
If that contract breaks down. then all social contracts break down.
Si tu ne l'écoutes pas, le contrat social est rompu.
And we descend into anarchy.
Et tout dégénère en une anarchie.
It must be hell inside your head.
Ça doit être l‘enfer dans ta tête.
At times.
Parfois.
Guys. we have a code red.
On a un code rouge.
Code red. the hospital emergency alert? The computer worm?
A l'hôpital ? Un Virus informatique ?
Or the cherry-flavored soft drink from the makers of Mountain Dew?
Ou le soda a la cerise de Mountain Dew ?
l was going over the schematics on my Zero-G Toilet...
J'ai revu les plans de mes toilettes
...and I made a teeny-tiny mistake on the specifications for the diverter valve.
et j'ai fait une erreur riquiqui concernant la soupape de décharge.
How teeny-tiny?
Riquiqui comment ?
It's gonna fail after about ten flushes.
Dix chassés d‘eau tirées et c‘est fini.
-But the mission is for six months. -That's the code red.
- Ils sont en mission pour six mois. - D'où le code rouge.
It's kind of like a jack-in-the-box. No one knows exactly when...
C‘est un vrai piégé. On ne sait pas quand,
...but at some point. something way worse than a puppet...
mais la surprise ne sera pas agréable.
Have you notified NASA?
As-tu prévenu la NASA ?
You crazy? What am I gonna say? I screwed up your toilet...
T'es fou ? Pour dire quoi ? J'ai foiré les toilettes.
...and pretty soon there's gonna be crap floating all over your nice space station?
Et dela merde va flotter autour de votre jolie station spatiale ?
What are you gonna do?
Oue comptes-tu faire ?
I'm gonna figure out how to fix it. then I'll tell them.
Trouver comment la réparer et ensuite leur dire.
So. what do you need us for?
En quoi on t'est utiles ?
He can't figure out how to fix it.
Il ne sait pas comment la réparer.
You said you were gonna be supportive.
Tu as promis de me soutenir.
I'm trying. But you have to admit. this is pretty damn funny.
J‘essaie. Mais reconnais que c‘est très drôle.
I agree.
C‘est vrai.
It's a juxtaposition of the nature of space exploration...
La juxtaposition de l‘exploration spatiale
...against the banality of a malfunctioning toilet...
et d‘une chose si banale que des toilettes défectueuses est comique.
Check your messages.
Ecoute tes messages.
All right. this is an exact duplicate of the Wolowitz Zero-Gravity...
Bien, c‘est une réplique exacte du système Wolowitz
...Human Waste Disposal System as deployed on the Space Station.
pour l‘élimination des déchets de la station spatiale.
Don't you mean the Wolowitz Zero-Gravity...
Tu veux dire le systéme Wolowitz pour la distribution, non ?
Good one. yeah.
Elle est bonne, oui.
lt's hilarious. Now.
C‘est hilarant. Bon...
Here's an approximation of the spare parts available on the space station.
Voici, en gros, les pièces que l'on trouve dans la station.
We gotta find a way. using nothing but this. to reinforce this.
On doit réparer ça, avec ces pièces,
So the waste material avoids the turbine.
pour que les déchets évitent la turbine.
You mean. so it doesn't hit the fan?
Pour ne pas être dans le caca ?
You know. I have to say I thought the toilet humor...
Je pensais que ce genre d'humour serait moins drôle à force de répétition.
Apparently. there is no law of diminishing comedic returns with space poop.
Mais les blagues de caca les plus longues sont les meilleures.
-Hey. Leonard. -Hey. Stuart.
- Salut. T'es occupé ? - Salut.
Classified. Leonard.
Top secret, Leonard.
Yeah. it's a regular Manhattan Project.
Oui, un vrai projet Manhattan.
-What's up? -Well. tonight's my date with Penny.
- Qu'y a-t-il ? - Je sors avec Penny.
And we haven't been able to connect by phone--
Je n'ai pas pu te joindre au téléphone...
-Yeah. I'm sorry. It's been broken. -Or e-mail.
- Il est cassé. - Ni par e-mail.
Yeah. that's broken too. Everything's broken.
C‘est cassé aussi. Tout est cassé.
Anyway. I was just wondering if you had any last-minute advice.
Est-ce que tu aurais un conseil de dernière minute ?
All right. Well. off the top of my head...
Bon. Là, tout de suite,
...you know. I think the most important thing with Penny is to go really slow.
le plus important avec Penny, c‘est d‘y aller doucement.
I mean. glacial.
D'être glacial.
-Okay. -You know. guys come on to her...
- Bien. - On la drague tout le temps,
Be a little shy.
Joue au timide.
And don't make too much eye contact.
Et ne la regarde pas trop.
And you know. treat her with. like. cool detachment.
Traité-Ia avec détachement.
And. you know. fear.
- Et avec crainte. - Çrainte ?
Well. that plays right into my wheelhouse.
C‘est ma spécialité.
Good. good. Well. you kids have fun tonight.
Tant mieux. Amusez-vous bien, ce soir.
Thanks. Leonard.
Merci, Leonard.
What is that thing anyway?
C‘est quoi, ce truc ?
You don't know what this is?
Tu ne sais pas ?
-No. -Good. get out.
- Non. - Tant mieux, dégagé.
Be afraid of Penny. Nice. very crafty.
Sois craintif de Penny. Trés astucieux.
It wasn't bad advice. It just wasn't particularly helpful.
Ce n‘était pas un mauvais conseil. Plus un handicap.
For what it's worth. my mother says that when we deceive for personal gain...
Ma mère dit que quand on trompe quelqu‘un,
...we make Jesus cry.
Jésus pleuré.
All right. what if we use this two-inch PVC...
On peut utiliser ce P.V.Ç. de 2 cm pour renforcer le support transversal.
No good. I mean. it might work for the Japanese and the Americans...
Non, ça irait pour les Japonais et les Américains,
...but have you seen the size of the Russians they got up there?
mais t‘as vu les mastocs russes ?
This thing has to hold up against a hearty potato-based diet.
Ça doit supporter un bon gros régime de patates.
| feel terrible.
Je m'en veux.
Maybe if you were helping. you'd feel better about yourself.
Si tu nous aidais, tu irais mieux.
l deliberately tried to sabotage Stuart's date with Penny.
J'ai volontairement saboté Ie rancard de Stuart.
Of course you feel terrible. You completely screwed up your karma. dude.
Tu t'en veux et tu as bousillé ton karma.
You don't really believe in that superstition. do you?
Tu ne crois pas a cette superstition ?
It's not superstition. it's practically Newtonian.
C‘est quasiment newtonien.
For every action. there's an equal and opposite reaction.
Chaque action entraîne une réaction opposée.
Leonard pretends to be a friend. and acts like a two-faced bitch.
Léonard prétend être un ami, mais il est faux-cui.
Therefore. he is reborn as a banana slug.
Il va donc se réincarner en limace-banane.
It's actually a very elegant system. You know. what goes around comes around.
Un système élégant. Oui sème le vent, récolte la tempête.
Speaking of what goes around comes around....
En parlant de récolter...
Okay. look.
Bien, écouté.
Instead of trying to reinforce this structure here...
Plutôt que de renforcer la structure,
...what if we ran another line. bypassed it entirely?
on pourrait faire une dérivation, ici.
Won't work. The diameter of the tubing is insufficient.
Ça n‘ira pas. Le diamètre est insuffisant.
What if we reposition the collection tank?
Et si on repositionne la chasse ?
It won't work. No way to mount it.
Ça n‘ira pas. Impossible à monter.
Here's an idea. What if I change my name...
Je sais. Je peux changer de nom
...and go live with my cousin and her husband. Avi. in Israel?
et partir Vivre avec ma cousine et son mari, en Israël ?
That could work.
Ça pourrait marcher.
-Morning. -Morning. What's up?
- Bonjour. - Bonjour. Qu'y a-t-il ?
Nothing. We just pulled an all-nighter trying to fix a Zero-Gravity pasta maker.
Rien. On a passé la nuit à réparer une machine à pâtes spatiale.
Great. so how'd it go with Stuart last night?
Super, c‘était comment avec Stuart ?
I really don't wanna talk about it.
Je préfère ne pas en parler.
Yeah. Right. Sure.
Oui. D‘accord.
But. you know. the thing is. before you guys went out...
Avant votre rancard,
-I spoke to him and |-- -I said I don't wanna talk about it.
-je lui ai dit que... - Je ne veux pas en parler.
-Okay. I kind of feel res-- -Look. Leonard.
- D‘accord, je m‘en... - Non, Leonard.
What goes on is none of your business. So just leave it alone. okay?
Ça ne te concerne pas. Alors, arrête, d'accord ?
If you really want to clean up your karma. go get my freaking latte.
Si tu veux purifier ton karma. ramène—moi mon café latte.
Hang on. I think I've got this.
Attendez, je sais.
Help me see if we can wedge this piece of PVC behind the support rod.
Voyons si on peut caler ce P.V.Ç. derrière la colonne.
You're overestimating the strength of the substructure you're building.
Tu surestimes la force de ta structuré.
-Sheldon. I know what I'm doing. -If you knew what you were doing...
Je sais ce que je fais.
Howard. wait.
Howard, attends.
Why don't you use this instead of the PVC to keep the filter assembly in place?
Utilise ça plutôt que le P.V.Ç. pour maintenir le filtre.
Because this is not a spare part from the space station.
Ce n‘est pas une pièce dans la station.
This is the thing from the pizza box that keeps the lid from touching the cheese.
Ça empêche le couvercle dela pizza de toucher la pizza.
Is that what that's for? In India. the lid just touches the cheese.
En Inde, le couvercle touche la pizza.
We also have rampant poverty and periodic outbreaks of cholera...
La pauvreté fait des ravages, le choléra aussi,
...so a little cardboard in our cheese is no biggie.
alors ce truc pour la pizza, on s'en passé.
-Where you going? -Comic-book store.
- Où vas-tu ? - Au magasin.
Oh. an excellent idea. I could certainly use a break.
Excellente idée. Une pause me fera du bien.
-Me too. -You can go to the comic book store...
- Moi aussi. - Tu iras au magasin
...when man can once again safely poop in space.
quand l‘homme pourra faire caca dans l‘espace.
Why does Leonard get to go?
Pourquoi Léonard peut partir ?
Because he's upset over his situation with Penny.
Il est contrarié a cause de Penny.
And if I have to hear about it again. I'm gonna kick him in his ovaries.
S'il en parle encore, je lui botte les ovaires.
-Thanks for understanding. Howard. HOWARD: I got your back. sister.
- Merci bien. - C‘est normal, frangine.
All right. I think we've got a prototype ready to test. Hand me that Tupperware.
On a un prototype à tester. Passe—moi ce Tupperware.
-That's heavy. -Damn right. it's heavy.
- C‘est lourd. - Tu m'étonnes.
It's my mother's meatloaf.
C‘est le pain de viande de ma mère.
It's been testing toilets for generations.
Il teste des toilettes depuis des générations.
I must say. Howard...
Si jamais
...I think a detailed letter to MIT describing your current circumstances...
on expliquait au M.I.T. tes problèmes actuels,
...might entitle you to a refund on your Master's degree.
ils te rembourseraient peut-ètre tes études.
Okay. simulated zero-gravity human waste disposal test with meatloaf analog.
Test de système d‘élimination avec pain de viande analogue.
In three. two. one.
Dans trois, deux, un.
Fascinating.
Fascinant.
What do you think the problem is?
Alors, quel est le probléme ?
Not enough bread crumbs.
Pas assez de chapelure.
-Hey. Stuart. I need to talk to you. -Sure. what's up?
- Salut, je dois te parler. - Qu'y a-t-il ?
I think I gave you some bad advice about Penny and I want to apologize.
Je t'ai donné un mauvais conseil, je m‘excuse.
No. your advice was great.
C‘était un super conseil.
-It was? -Oh. yeah. going slow really worked.
- Ah bon ? - Doucement, ca a marché.
You're kidding.
Tu plaisantes.
Never worked for me.
Ça n‘a jamais marché avec moi.
Yeah. last night at dinner I did what you told me.
J'ai fait ce que tu m'as dit.
I went really slow. I kept my distance...
J'ai gardé mes distances
...and two bottles of wine later. we were making out in my car.
et après 2 bouteilles de vin, on s‘embrassait.
Wine? I didn't say to give her wine.
Je ne t'ai pas parlé de vin !
It doesn't matter. That's where it all went to hell.
Peu importe. Après, ça a dérapé.
During the kissing?
Lors du baiser ? Pourquoi ?
What did you do. sneeze in her mouth? I did that to a girl once.
Tu lui as éternué dans la bouche ? Ça m‘est arrivé.
No. everything was good and really hot.
Non, tout allait bien, c‘était chaud.
And I said. oh. Penny...
Et j'ai dit : “Oh, Penny.“
...and right where she was supposed to say. "Oh. Stuart“ she said...
Et au lieu de dire : "Oh, Stuart.“ Elle a dit...
. . .your name.
ton nom.
-Leonard? -That is your name. right?
- Léonard ? - C‘est bien ton nom ?
Yeah. No. yeah. it is.
Oui. Non, oui, c'est...
Wow. I'm sorry.
Je suis désolé.
That must've been the last thing you wanted to hear.
Ce n‘était pas ce que tu voulais entendre.
Well. it beats. “You know I'm a dude. right?“
C‘est mieux que : "Tu sais que je suis un mec, hein ?“
Yeah. it was pretty bad.
Oui, c‘était nui.
No doubt. no doubt.
J'imagine, j'imagine.
Okay. well...
Bon, alors...
-...|'m sorry it didn't work out. -Not your fault.
- désolé. - Tu n‘y es pour rien.
Yeah. how about that?
Oui, c‘est étonnant !
-See you soon. -Yep. sure.
- A bientôt. - Bien sûr.
Yes. I understand. Classified. We'll keep it all classified.
Oui, je comprends. Ça restera top secret.
No one has to know anything about this but you and me.
Personne ne le saura a part vous et moi.
What's classified?
Top secret ?
Howard's space toilet. I'll tell you later.
Ses toilettes spatiales. Je t'expliquerai.
Well. they've deployed our solution. Let's just all hope it works.
Ils ont utilisé notre solution. Espérons que ca marche.
I don't see why I have to worry.
Pourquoi s‘inquiéter ?
My career's not hanging in the balance.
Ma carrière n‘est pas en jeu.
That was a joke.
C‘était une plaisanterie.
It's funny because it's true.
C‘est drôle, car c‘est vrai.
Leonard. could you pass the soy sauce. please?
Leonard, tu me passés la sauce soja ?
-|'m sorry. were you talking to me? -Yeah. I said Leonard.
- Pardon, tu disais ? - Je disais, Leonard.
Yes. you did. didn't you?
Oui, c‘est vrai, n'est-ce pas ?
What the hell is that?
C‘est quoi, ce truc ?
Meatloaf.
Un pain de Viande.
What was it doing on the ceiling?
Pourquoi c‘était au plafond ?
That's classified.
C‘est top secret.
ASTRONAUT [OVER RADIO]: Houston, International Space Station.
Houston, station spatiale internationale.
We have a little situation up here.
On a un petit problème.
We 'd like to make an unscheduled space walk.
On aimerait sortir dans l'espace.
MAN [OVER RADIO]: [35, Houston...
I. S. S., Houston,
which crew members would be involved in this EVA?
qui veut effectuer cette sortie ?
ASTRONAUT: Houston, we 'd all like to step outside for a few minutes.
Houston, on veut tous sortir un moment.
MAN: [35, I'm afraid we can 't authorize that.
I.S.S., on ne peut pas l‘autoriser.
ASTRONAUT: Houston, this is more of an FYI call.
Houston, c‘est une requête sérieuse.
We are basically out the door.
On est quasiment a‘ la porte.
[ENGLISH SDH]
[FRENCH]